Inventory of the Fred L. Walker papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Fred L. Walker papers
1889-1969
1915-1947
93001
Hoover Institution Archives
9 manuscript boxes, 4 oversize boxes, 1 oversize folder (11.75 linear feet)
Memoirs, diaries, speeches, correspondence, news clippings, printed matter, photographs, and memorabilia relating primarily to the American military campaign in Italy during World War II, especially to the Battle of the Rapido River. Also includes material on the Second Battle of the Marne in World War I, American troops in the Philippines, the Punitive Expedition into Mexico in 1916, and the Texas National Guard.
Walker, Fred L. (Fred Livingood), 1887-1969.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1993.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1887 Born in Fairfield County, Ohio
1911 Graduated from Ohio State University with a degree in engineering and joined the Army as second lieutenant
1911-1914 Served in the Philippines with 13th U.S. Infantry
1914-1916 Served with 17th Infantry in the Punitive Expedition into Mexico
1917-1918 Served with the 30th Infantry Regiment in France
1918 Battalion Commander during the Second Battle of the Marne and awarded the Distinguished Service Cross
1927-1932 Infantry School instructor
1941-1944 Appointed commanding general of the 36th Infantry Division in Texas and fought at the Battle of Salerno at Paestum, Rapido River, Cassino, and Mt. Artemisio
1944 Awarded Second Distinguished Service Cross
1946-1947 Retired from the army as a major general and appointed lieutenant general and commander of the Texas National Guard
1969 Died in Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection consists of diaries, memoirs, speeches, correspondence, news clippings, printed matter, photographs, and memorabilia of Fred Livingood Walker, Commander of the 36th Infantry Division in World War II. Walker's papers detail his military career and relate to American troops in the Philippines in 1912, the Punitive Expedition into Mexico in 1916, and the Second Battle of the Marne in World War I. The bulk of the collection focuses on the 36th Division's campaign in Italy during World War II, especially to the Battle of the Rapido River, and Walker's later commandment of the Texas National Guard. The collection is arranged into five groups: Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Military Career file, Photographs, and Scrapbooks and Printed material.
Related Collection
Fred L. (Fred Livingood) Walker typescript: Mission impossible at Cassino: the first assault across the Rapido River near Cassino in World War II, January 1944, Hoover Institution Archives
Texas. National Guard.; United States. Army--History--Punitive Expedition into Mexico, 1916.; United States. Army--Officers.; United States. Army. American Expeditionary Forces.; United States. Army. Infantry Division, 36th.; Marne, 2nd Battle of the, France, 1918.; Rapido River, Battle of the, 1944.; United States--Armed Forces--Philippines.; United States--National Guard.; World War, 1914-1918--Campaigns--France.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Italy.
- Correspondence, 1944-1947
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains letters and telegrams to and from Walker after his return from deployment in Italy in 1944 and mostly consists of correspondence from his tenure as commander of the Texas National Guard and Director of Military Training with Army Service Forces. The correspondence maintains the original order of the creator and is arranged into personal and professional correspondence.
  - Personal correspondence, 1944-1947
    - 1944 July - September (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - 1944 October - December (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - 1945 January - June 30 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - A-J, 1945-1947 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - K-S, 1945-1947 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - Keystone Wood Preserving Company, 1946 (Box-folder 9: 5)
    - 1946-1947 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - Invitations, RSVP response letters, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Professional correspondence, 1945-1947
    - Adjutant General's Office, War Department, 1945-1947 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Ainsworth, H. Miller, Colonel, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Albert, John E., Colonel, Air Corps, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Army Service Forces, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Barron, Gaines, Colonel, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - Biographical sketches and requests, 1944-1946 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - Bradley, Omar, General, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - Chase, Thorton, Colonel, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    - Clark, Mark, General, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 9)
    - Dahlquist, John, Major General, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 10)
    - Dawes, B. G., 1945 (Box-folder 2: 11)
    - Delcher, Bill, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 12)
    - Films, battlefield reels, 1946 (Box-folder 2: 13)
    - Heraty, Francis (Mike), Colonel, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 14)
    - Hobson, W.H. (Bunny), 1945 (Box-folder 2: 15)
    - Hume, Edgan, Brigadier General, 1946 (Box-folder 2: 16)
    - Humphery, Walter, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 17)
    - Kelley, William, Captain, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 18)
    - Kerr, Clayton, Colonel, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 19)
    - O'Connell, Arthur, 1947 (Box-folder 2: 20)
    - Order of Saints Maurice and Lazarus, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 21)
    - Publicity, 1946 (Box-folder 2: 22)
    - Salerno Memorial, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 23)
    - Sevaried, Eric, 1946 (Box-folder 2: 24)
- Speeches and Writings, 1912-1947
  Consists of diaries and drafts of memoirs that relate to Walker's experiences in the military, which would later serve as material for his published memoir, From Texas to Rome, and speeches given upon his return from active duty and during his tenure as General of the Texas National Guard. Arranged by format.
  - Writings, 1912-1947
    - Diary and notebook, undated (Box-folder 2: 25)
    - Diaries, 1912-1941 (Box 3)
    - Memoirs, typescript drafts, undated (Box-folder 4: 1-5; 5: 1)
  - Speeches, 1944-1947
    - Untitled. speech, American Red Cross, undated (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - "Some of my experiences and conclusions arrived at as the result of my service in the Italian Theatre of Operations with the 36th Division," undated (Box-folder 5: 3)
    - Untitled. peech, State Board Conference, undated (Box-folder 5: 4)
    - 1944 July 7. speech, "Farewell Review by the Troops of the 36th Division at Paestum, Italy," 1944 (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - 1944 November 11. speech, talk before the American Legion in Columbus, Ohio, 1944 (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - 1944 November 28. speech, British Officers Dinner, 1944 (Box-folder 5: 7)
    - 1944 December 7. speech, New York- War Bond trip, 1944 (Box-folder 5: 8)
    - 1945 January 4. speech, dinner for Modern Small Arms and Ammunition Industry, 1945 (Box-folder 5: 9)
    - 1945 January 26. speech, The Civitan Club in Birmingham, Alabama, 1945 (Box-folder 5: 10)
    - 1945 January 29. speech, The Columbus Kiwanis Club, 1945 (Box-folder 5: 11)
    - 1945 March 14. speech, for radio broadcast Dallas Morning News, 1945 (Box-folder 5: 12)
    - 1945 March 17. speech notes, untitled, 1945 (Box-folder 5: 13)
    - 1945 May 8. announcement, "Victory in Europe," 1945 (Box-folder 5: 14)
    - 1945 May 15. speech, Detroit, Michigan, dedication of Hero's Square, 1945 (Box-folder 5: 15)
    - 1946 May 26. speech, reorganization of the Texas National Guard, 1946 (Box-folder 5: 16)
    - 1946 July 6. speech, Duty to Continued Peace in Austin, Texas, 1946 (Box-folder 5: 17)
    - 1946 September 5. speech, American Legion of Galveston, Texas, 1946 (Box-folder 5: 18)
    - 1946 November 11. speech, "Address of Governor-Elect Jester on the Occasion of the Return of the Colors to the State of Texas," 1946 (Box-folder 5: 19)
    - 1947 April 13. address, American Legion in Childress, Texas, 1947 (Box-folder 5: 20)
- Military Career File, 1918-1967
  Contains reports, bulletins, news clippings, memorandums, maps, and printed matter detailing United States military operations and Walker's military career. Arranged by subject, then chronologically.
  - World War I, 1918-1922, 1967
    - Marne Division bulletins and other printed matter, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 5: 21)
    - Barrage sheet of German tactics on Marne, 1918, 1967 July 15 (Box-folder 5: 22)
    - Campaign of 1918, Americans at the Second Battle of Marne, circa 1921-1922 (Box-folder 5: 23)
    - Battle of Verdun Illustrated Guide, undated (Box-folder 5: 24)
  - World War II, 1941-1946
    - Special orders, re: appointment lists, 1941-1945 (Box-folder 5: 25)
    - Publicity clippings, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 5: 26)
    - Italian campaign maps, 1940s (Box 9)
    - Fort Benning memorandums, 1945 January-February (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - Po Valley campaign printed matter, 1945 (Box-folder 6: 2)
    - Portrait presentation of Walker at the Texas Senate, 1945 April 30 (Box-folder 6: 3)
    - Retirement file with the Adjutant General Office, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 6: 4)
    - The Rapido River Crossing, Hearings before the Committee on Military Affairs from House of Representatives, 1946 February 20-1946 March 18, 1946 February 20 - March 18 (Box-folder 6: 5)
    - "Intermission at Cassino,", undated (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Texas National Guard lists, reports, plans, and constitution, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Charles Walker, awards and commendations, 1959 (Box-folder 6: 8)
- Photographs, 1889-1969
  Photographs include Walker's early years in the miltary from deployment to the Philippines and the Punitive Expedition, to World Wars I and II. The majority of the photographs are of the 36th Infantry Division activities during and after World War II. Also included are personal family photographs. Arranged chronologically by subject.
  - Family photographs, 1889-1945 (Box-folder 6: 10)
  - Troop B drills, Columbus, Ohio, photo album, 1908 (Box-folder 6: 11)
  - Family photographs while stationed in the Philippines, 1912-1915 (Box-folder 6: 12)
  - Portraits of Fred Walker, 1911-1947 (Box-folder 6: 13; 7: 1)
  - Punitive Expedition into Mexico, 1915-1917 (Box-folder 7: 2)
  - World War I, on the Banks of the Rhine and German soldiers prison camp, 1917-1919 (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - Fred Walker, Jr., 1928-1935, 1944 (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - 15th Infantry, Fort Lewis, Washington, photo album, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - The 36th Infantry Division, 1941-1969 (Box-folder 7: 5; 8: 1-3)
  - Campaign into Italy, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 8: 4-6)
  - Aerial shot of Area "E" terrain to Cassino, circa 1940s (Box 10)
  - Perasano, Italy, photo album, circa 1944 (Box-folder 8: 7)
  - Fort Benning, Infantry School and miscellaneous receptions and dinners, post 1944 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - P.R.O. photographs from Bunny (W. H.) Hobson, 1945 (Box-folder 9: 2)
  - Colonel Ainsworth Ranch, 1945 (Box-folder 9: 3)
  - Texas, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 9: 4)
- Scrapbooks and Printed Material, 1898-1968
  The scrapbooks contain photographs of the 36th Infantry Division's campaign from Africa into Italy, news clippings, and career and personal ephemera. Arranged by format.
  - Art prints, undated (Box 10)
  - Infantry in Battle (Box-folder 9: 6)
  - Reprint of "Instrument of Surrender" by Japanese government, circa 1945 (Box 10)
  - Certificate of appreciation from Chaplains Corps, Rome, Italy, 1944 July (Box 10)
  - Scrapbook, 1898-1940s (Box 11)
  - News clippings scrapbook, 1911-1968 (Box 12)
  - Photograph scrapbook, 1942-1944 (Box 13)